My husband was taken to Hospital 108 for scans
Chồng em bị đi bệnh viện 108 chiếu chụp
and tests, and they discovered he had an
và xét nghiệm thì phát hiện ra là bệnh
aortic aneurysm that could rupture at any time, meaning
phình động mạch chủ nó vỡ bất cứ lúc nào
he would die. He kept having fevers, then becoming delirious, not knowing
thì nó chết Cứ sốt xong mê man chả biết
anything, high fevers, chest pain, meaning he could
gì sốt cao tức ngực nghĩa là cứ thở thở
barely breathe, lying paralyzed for so long that the flesh started to rot, affecting three or four fingertips, the tailbone, and both heels. He was so full. He was terrified; every time he saw me, he cried. It was such a painful sight. On November 8th, we thought he wouldn't make it.
tưởng nó không qua khỏi rồi
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
Respectfully, to the Headmistress, respectfully to
Kính thưa cô chủ nhiệm Kính thưa toàn
all esteemed fellow practitioners, as in the Giap Son
thể các bạn quý đạo hữu như ở đạo tràng
Holy Meditation Center, there are
thánh định Giáp Sơn cũng có những cái
cases where, during the practice of
trường hợp trong quá trình tu tập mà cần
seeking the Buddha's teachings, one finds the Buddha's teachings miraculous. The
cầu Phật Pháp mà thấy Phật Pháp là nhiệm
husband of a Buddhist practitioner named Loi had an
mầu chồng của phật tử lời là đã mắc cái
aortic aneurysm and went for treatment
phình động mạch chủ mà cũng đi điều trị
at various hospitals, but upon returning home, he was
ở các bệnh viện nhưng khi về thì đã nằm
paralyzed. However, through practice, he
liệt Nhưng trong tu tập thì đã chuyển
transformed. I would like to invite Loi to
hóa sau đây cũng xin mời đạo hữu lời lên
share her story of karmic transformation. Please, Loi,
chia sẻ về câu chuyện chuyển nghiệp của
[Applause] Namo
[Vỗ tay]
Buddha Shakyamuni. Respectfully, to the
Nam Mô Phật Bổn Sư Thích Ca Mâu Ni với
Headmistress  Dear fellow
Kính bạch cô chủ nhiệm ở Kính thưa các
practitioners, My name is Nguyen Thi No, from
đạo hữu Em tên là Nguyễn Thị Nở ở thôn
Dong Phong village, Dong Coc commune, Luc Ngan district,
Đồng Phong xã Đồng Cốc huyện Lục Ngạn
Bac Giang province. I am a member
tỉnh Bắc Giang mình cần em sinh hoạt ở
of the Thai Tinh Jeoson Bac Giang Buddhist group,
tại đạo tràng thái tỉnh jeoson Bắc Giang
part of the Golden Chrysanthemum Club. In
thuộc câu lạc bộ cúc vàng năm 2020 tháng
June 2020, my husband had a high fever, followed by
6 năm 2020 là chồng em bị sốt cao xong
shortness of breath and chest tightness. We
thì khó thở tức ngực Thế là các cháu Các
took him to Hospital 108 for scans
con ấy mang đi bệnh viện 108 chiếu chụp
and tests, and they discovered he had
và xét nghiệm thì phát hiện ra là bệnh
aortic aneurysm. The doctor said that if
thành động mạch chủ bác sĩ bảo là nếu mà
surgery was necessary, we would have to order it from abroad because it was
phải mổ thì phải mua tiên đặt ở nước
n't available in our country.
được nước mình không có thế là bảo thế
They said the surgery
cao mổ thì hết liệu bao nhiêu tiền bảo
would cost 400 million VND. We hadn't prepared for it yet,
là hết 400 triệu Thế chưa Chuẩn bị được
so we went home. The doctor
thì là chưa mổ thì mới về về thì bác sĩ
gave us 20 days' worth of medication for treatment. They said
bán cho thuốc 20 ngày để điều trị Còn
if the condition improved, surgery wouldn't be necessary, but if
nếu mà nó dẹp lại thì không phải mổ nếu
it persisted, then surgery was required. After
mà nó vẫn phải ấy thì phải mổ thế là về
15 days of taking the medication, we took him to
15 ngày thuốc thì là các con lại mang đi
Bach Mai Hospital for examination. They
bệnh viện Bạch Mai Khám khám cũng chẩn
diagnosed the same condition, saying that
đoán ra cái bệnh đấy của cái bệnh này
the sooner the surgery is performed, the better, to prevent rupture at any
càng mổ sớm càng tốt không có vỡ bất cứ
time.  Then it died. That was it, lying
lúc nào thì nó chết Thế là xong nằm ở
there, the family decided to operate, and
đấy thì gia đình quyết định mổ thì hết
after the surgery, it cost 290 million VND. 290
sau cuộc mổ đấy là hết 290 triệu 290
million VND for treatment at the hospital for
triệu thì điều trị ở đấy là bệnh viện là
20 days. After 20 days, the
20 ngày 20 ngày xong thì lúc bấy giờ này
epidemic (as you wrote) broke out
là cái dịch cô viết Nó bùng phát mạnh
so strongly that the hospital allowed it to go home for
quá thế là bệnh viện mới cho về nhà để
outpatient treatment. But at home, it kept
điều trị ngoại trú Thế là cứ về nhà thì
recurring, feverish,
cứ tái phát đi tái phát lại cứ sốt xong
delirious, not knowing anything, high fever, chest tightness,
mê man chả biết gì sốt cao tức ngực
meaning it was just breathing heavily. Every month, it was a month in the
nghĩa là cứ thở thở mà cứ mỗi một tháng
emergency room. Twice, on
là đi cấp cứu một tháng Hai lần mùng 8
November 8th, we thought it wouldn't make it. It kept breathing, but its muscles were
tháng 11 thì là tưởng nó không qua khỏi
stiff. November 8th,
rồi cứ cứ thở thì lại cứng cứng 8 tháng
2020. The fever was so high,
11 năm nào Năm 2020 Thế là sốt quá thì
I gave it medicine, but it didn't know what to do. Then I took
em cho uống thuốc cũng không biết rồi
the milk bottle and put it in
uống nước Thế là lấy cái cái sữa cho vào
its mouth, and it started to drink. Right on time, its jaw
mồm thì uống thì lại đúng giờ là hàm
stiffened, biting down hard on the tube. I squeezed it to make it round,
cứng cắn chặt cái ống à bóp cho nó tròn
but it didn't know how to suck. Then I
thì lại không biết hút rồi thì biết em
squeezed it, and it wanted to swallow. So, that's
bóp vào cho cho chị muốn nuốt Thôi thì
when it was the first day, and it did
tức là lúc bấy giờ là ngày đầu đầu tiên
n't know what to do anymore.
mới biết là không biết được nữa còn đợt
Before that, it could still suck and eat.  Even when lying down, I
trước là vẫn hút được còn ăn được nằm
still needed help with bowel and bladder control, relying on family members. If I just stayed in bed, the
thì vẫn bón đại tiểu tiện nhờ người nhà
fever would have been
thôi chứ không cứ nằm nhiệt thế là xuống
unbearable. When I went to the district hospital, they didn't dare accept the case, so they referred me to the provincial hospital. So I took the X-ray results to the hospital and they said, "Oh, this disease can't be treated here." So I
bệnh này thì không ở đây không chữa được
went to
Vậy nên Trung ương Thế là đi đến bệnh
Bach Mai Hospital, completed the procedures, and
viện Bạch Mai là làm thủ tục xong là hai
was there for treatment at 2 AM.
giờ sáng hai giờ sáng nằm ở đấy điều trị
The doctor said they needed to see
thì bác sĩ bảo xem xem là xét nghiệm xem
what was causing the high fever, and that I would have to pay for the tests. The
nó là tại cái gì mà nó lại sốt cao như
doctor took samples from my teeth, nose, and
bác sĩ lại lấy nước vợt ở răng này ở mũi
eyes for testing, but they still couldn't find the
nửa mắt mình xét nghiệm vẫn không biết
cause of the fever.
là nguyên nhân ở đâu mà sốt thế thì
After a few days, the doctor sent me home, saying, "
là ở đâu có mấy hôm mình bác sĩ lại cho
Just isolate yourself," because they did
về bảo thôi về cách ly thôi chứ không
n't dare let me stay there. My family was so
không dám cho ở đấy gia đình cứ Hoang
worried and anxious. They went to see a fortune teller, who invited me to perform
Mang lo lắng gì đi xem bói thì mời mình
rituals, but there was no
cúng về cúng rồi các kiểu cũng không
improvement. I was so worried and scared.
thấy tiến triển tí nào mà lo lắm lo sợ
I kept crying whenever I saw my husband,
Thế là em nhìn thấy cứ nhìn thấy chồng
because of this terrible situation.  My
là khóc nên là vì cái cảnh lại khổ lắm
father abandoned me, he went to join the army, leaving me
thì trước kia bố bỏ con bố đi bộ đội đã
orphaned from the age of six. My
bỏ chết bỏ mồ côi bố từ lúc lên 6 tuổi
mother only gave birth to two daughters, and then she
mẹ sinh được có hai chị em thế là mẹ lại
went to see Tram, her son-in-law, and kept telling her to go to Tram. She
lên Trâm trong con rể cứ nặn cho con rể
kept telling her son-in-law, "Oh, I'm so miserable, my child.
Nếu mà trong mẹ lại bảo khổ lắm con ơi
Now I only rely on you. Your father
Bây giờ mẹ chỉ nhờ có con bây giờ bố con
abandoned you, and now your son-in-law has abandoned me." So my
bỏ con rồi bây giờ lại con rể lại bỏ mẹ
mother and I confided in each other, sharing our
sẻ như sau thế mà không mẹ nhà con không
feelings. But no, my mother said, "It's okay, Mom. I'm fine." We kept encouraging each other, and so we kept seeing Tram, trying all sorts of things, but nothing worked. Then Mai Duyen Lanh met her granddaughter, a fellow devotee,
gặp được kính cháu tại tại đạo hữu của
and asked, "Grandma, are you going to
mình đến và bà ơi thế Bà con có về chùa
Ba Vang Temple?" She replied, "I don't know
Ba Vàng không và không biết chùa Ba Vàng
Ba Vang Temple, but it's very miraculous,
thì thôi đâu thì chùa Ba Vàng Nhiệm Màu
Grandma.
lắm bà ạ
If you want to go, Grandma, I'll go too. I'll go
Cháu bà có đi không cháu cũng đi phải có
someday, even when I'm 30, I'll go." So, she went, and it was a
Thế hôm nào đi nữa đến 30 thì 30 bạc
fortunate coincidence. She met the woman in the white dress, and then she met the man and
duyên May lại gặp được cô áo trắng chưa
the other women in the
Ông ấy với lại mấy cô đạo tràng ở trong
temple, the officials in the temple.
đạo tràng cán bộ trong đạo tràng Thế là
Then the women helped her.  She went on the 8th
các cô trợ duyên ở thế thì chị đi Mùng 8
and then returned to take refuge in the Three Jewels. Yes, she returned and took refuge.
là chị về lại quy y Tam Bảo Ừ thế là
After taking refuge, on the
cũng về quy y quy y xong cái là cái mùng
10th, the children came to the family to share information
10 thì các em nó về gia đình chia sẻ cho
about her condition. That's when, on
Để xem là bệnh tình của Như thế nào Thế
December 16th, 2020, a
là mới sợ 16 tháng 12 năm 2020 thì đã có
nun came to the market to perform the rituals for the nun. The nun sent
cô đến chợ duyên cho cô Đạo Tràng Như cử
two fellow practitioners to the market to perform the rituals.
hai bạn đạo hữu đến chợ duyên làm xong
Then, my nephew, who calls my husband "
đâu đấy Rồi cái thằng cháu gọi chồng em
uncle," said, "What are you doing, Grandma?
là là ông chú nó bảo thế bà làm cái gì
Can you do something to help Grandpa and Grandma? You've been serving Grandpa for
thế này bảo bà làm được cho ông cháu đỡ
years and months, dealing with all the mess and suffering.
không Bà Hầu ông mấy năm mấy tháng trời
If you can
của bê cứt bê đái khổ lắm rồi Thì bà làm
help, Grandma, you can help them, Grandpa and Grandma, and Grandpa and
cho đỡ thì đỡ khổ ông cháu ông đỡ khổ bà
Grandma." Then he went home, and I
khổ chú em cháu nó thế là nó về thì em
bought a piece of land elsewhere for my
lại mua cái miếng đất ở chỗ khác đi cho
son to live on. I only told my
thằng con nó ở đấy thì chỉ nói cho con
two daughters-in-law, not my
hai con dâu thôi chứ không nói cho con
son, so I couldn't see him. I shared
không gặp được con con trai thì chia sẻ
with my son, "Today, I'm doing this, so you
với con của hôm nay mẹ làm như thế thì
children should prepare everything for me so that the nuns can come and
các con sắm hết cho mẹ để cho các cô đến
do it." Then my nephew called my son and asked, "
làm cho thế là thằng cháu nó điện cho
What are you doing, Grandma?"
thằng con trai nó về bà làm cái gì ý chú
Go and see what the owls are flying around. They're all over the
về mà xem cú cú bay Bái cái gì đầy hết
yard, the house, even the altar. So I
cả sân cả nhà cả cả bàn thờ Thế nên là
told her to go home. "Mom, what are you doing?" she said. "
con bảo nó về nó Mẹ làm cái gì thế này
Mom, I'm doing this to ease
còn Mẹ làm cái này để cho bố con đỡ cho
Dad's suffering, to ease Mom's suffering. I'm in front of her, Dad's suffering is
đỡ khổ mẹ con mình con ở trước nó khổ bố
10 parts, Mom and I will endure 5 or 6
con 10 phần mẹ con mình chịu khó 5 6
parts. Is there any more for Mom to do to Uncle? Mom, you
phần thôi Có nữa để mẹ làm chú khổ không
can't do that!" she said. "
Mẹ không được làm đâu mà không miệng con
What are you doing?" I just listened to Mom. Then she
cứ nghe Mẹ bảo thế là nó Mẹ làm cái gì
went back to the aunt's house. That
thế nào con thế là nó về dưới cô thế là
night, the aunts went to the
tối các cô lên chợ duyên cho Úi giồi ôi
matchmaking market. Oh my god, going to the matchmaking market was so great!
lên chợ duyên cho thì mừng quá rồi rét
Nearly 20 people came to help that night. The
mướt gần 20 người đến trợ duyên tối
next day, my nephew called his son-in-
trước hôm sau cái thằng cháu nó gọi cả
law, daughter, and
con rể con gái
son's clothes, then they cooked rice, ate, and came home
quần áo con trai đến rồi nấu cơm ăn say
drunk. He said, "Mom, are you going to get rid of this? Let me have
rượu về nữa Nó bảo mẹ có bỏ cái này đi
three more mornings." He
không con ơi để cho mẹ ba buổi sáng nữa
called to disrupt things, to cause
rồi gọi lên là phá đám tập trung vào gọi
trouble, to prevent her from practicing Buddhism. So,
để phá đám không cho tu nữa Thế nên uống
drunk, he said, "Mom, are you going to get rid of it?
rượu say nó bảo mẹ có bỏ không bỏ con ơi
Let me have three more mornings. Let me ask
để cho mẹ ba buổi sáng nữa để mẹ xin
the aunts for permission, let me ask them what they want."
phép các cô xem mẹ hỏi thế nào nữa thôi
I just went outside and he came in.  She took
mình vừa đi ra ngoài tôi nó vào nó cầm
all the flower vases, then the rice bowls used for offering to Buddha, and
hết lọ hoa rồi cắm hoa rồi thì cốc gạo
threw them all away, breaking everything. After that,
thờ phật ý vứt đi hết vỡ hết Xong cái
she went home, destroyed everything, and then left. So, only my
thì nó về nó phá xong rồi nó về hết nên
husband and I were left to
tôi cũng còn lại được mỗi hai vợ chồng
take care of each other and our two grandchildren.
chăm nhau với hai đứa cháu ba đứa cháu
From that day on, every day, at
thế là từ hôm ý là cứ ngày nào cũng cứ 5
4:00 AM, I would wake up to practice meditation, cook rice, and chant prayers, offering
giờ 4:00 sáng là dậy tu tập nấu cơm cắm
rice and meditating.
cơm tôi dậy tụng kinh cúng cơm tu tập
We have a family that chants prayers and offers rice, so
Nhà mình có tụng kinh cúng cơm cho nên
we offer rice to the number 8 goddess.
là cúng cơm là mình cũng cơm cho bà số 8
Yes, at first, people said, "
đấy Vâng thì bắt đầu là mọi người bảo
What's the point of all this offering?" But actually, I do it
cúng gì cũng lắm thế nhưng thực ra mình
myself; I don't hire a monk or
tự cúng mà có đi mời ông thầy cúng có
spend any money. It's just a bowl of rice and a cup of
mất đồng tiền nào đâu Cơm có bát cơm
water, that's all. After eating, we just
chén nước chứ có gì đâu Chứ lấy sau ăn
throw away the rice grains. At night,
có vứt không hạt gạo luôn Tối thì làm
what do I do? At night, I serve my
thế nào Tối thì làm phục vụ phục vụ
husband. In the morning, at 4:00 AM, I wake up, cook
chồng sáng thì cứ Ba 4:00 sáng là Dậy
rice, meditate, and then
cắm cơm xong
feed my
tu xong cái thì lại bón cho chồng cho
husband. He just lies there feeding me, and then I
chồng cứ nằm đấy bón cho chồng xong thì
take the grandchildren to school. Meanwhile,
lại đưa cháu đi học trong khi đó chồng
my husband is bedridden and has rotting
em nằm liệt vị nhiều quá xong bị thối
flesh, even three or four fingertips and the tailbone
thịt của thối đến ba bốn đầu ngón ngón
are rotting.  He had amputated heels on
tay nữa cái xương cụt là cái xương cụt
both feet. So,
hai bên gót chân này nữa Thế là cứ một
twice a day, I would wash the foul-smelling area
ngày hai lần rửa cho chồng cái cái chỗ
in the middle of his feet, bandage it, and
thối đóng ở giữa băng băng bó cũng như
take care of him and our grandchildren while practicing meditation. Then, at the
thế chăm chồng chăm cháu lại tu Thế là
Dharma assembly, I practiced for a certain period of time
hôm đạo tràng Thế là mình tu khoảng thời
before the transformation occurred. It was about 10 days, maybe
gian bao lâu thì chuyển hóa cứ 10 đâu có
a month of
được một tháng
support. On December 16th, and then on
trợ duyên hôm 16 tháng 12 thì đến hai
January 10th, he naturally sat up.
mùng 10 tháng giêng là tự nhiên ngồi dậy
Do you see, dear fellow practitioners? He suddenly
được cô ạ Các Quý đạo hữu thấy không Tự
sat up, which made me so happy and excited that I immediately called
nhiên ngồi dậy được cho là mới phấn khởi
Ms.
quá sung sướng quá mới điện cho cô gạo
Gạo and said, "Ms. Gạo, he suddenly
luôn bảo cô Gạo ơi anh ấy tự nhiên anh
sat up!" I was on my way home from work, and
ngồi được rọi rồi Đang về làm việc thỉnh
occasionally I would ask, "Did you take any additional medicine during
thoảng có gạo mới bảo thế có thêm trong
that time?" It cost
cái thời gian ấy tu ấy có thêm cái loại
7 to 3 million VND at Bach Mai Hospital, and until
7 đến 3 triệu bệnh viện Bạch Mai đến bây
now, I haven't bought a single additional
giờ không thêm một không mua một dòng
medicine or had to go to the emergency room twice a month.
thuốc nào không phải đi mỗi một tháng
From then until now, I haven't been to the
Cứu Thế từ lúc từ tới giờ chưa đi bệnh
hospital once, haven't spent any
viện một lần nào chưa chưa hạnh phúc
money on medicine, and now,
đồng tiền thuốc nào và bây giờ hiện tại
how is he? He can walk normally again.
thì như thế nào dám mạnh đi lại bình
If this medicine is from Buddha, it
thường rồi Nếu mà đây thuốc của phật
doesn't cost money to buy.  But you have to know what you're losing, what you're
không mất tiền mua nhưng phải biết mất
losing is effort. So, during the practice session, I told
gì mất công sức đấy Thế hôm tu tập nói
the story, and by the 20th, he could
câu chuyện thế là đến 20 thì ngồi được
sit up. After practicing and
dậy ngồi được dậy thì cứ tu tập xong hồi
dedicating the merits to the departed souls, I lifted him
hướng cho các vong linh xong là lại Nhấc
up so he could sit up, and then
lên cho chồng cho ngồi sồn sồn này xong
he would turn around and go back to his normal state. He would
anh lại quay lại chứ lại cứ bò cứ bò qua
n't keep crawling across the bed like this, and then he'd keep going. For example, the couple would help each other walk. At first, when they came back from the hospital, generally speaking, out of 10 people, 11 fathers died, they couldn't make it through Tet.
không không thể qua khỏi được cái Tết
Their grandchildren loved him so much, they couldn't make it through
này các cháu họ thương của ông không thể
Tet. I still practiced, and by
qua khỏi được cái Tết này em vẫn tu tập
the 10th, he could sit up. By the 20th,
cứ đến mùng 10 thì ngồi được dậy đến 20
he could walk, and then he started
thì ông ấy đi men được xong đến Vâng đến
walking. Then, by February, the two of us were
tập đi xong đến tháng 2 thì là hai vợ
helping each other.
chồng cứ dìu nhau cho em khác ở bên đây
He held a stick, and
ông cầm một cái gậy anh cầm cái gậy thì
we helped each other walk around the house, then out to the
dìu nhau đi trong nhà xong lại đến ra
yard, out to the porch. By March,
sân ra sân Ra hiên xong đến tháng 3 thì
he could walk on his own with a stick.
là ông ấy tự là chống được gậy đi ra sân
And in this dark, fleshy place, his nephew,
còn cái chỗ tối thịt này thì cái thằng
the military doctor, helped him.  It just
cái thằng cháu bác sĩ của quân y nó mới
went into this place, so deep, so deep like this, does it have to be
vào cái chỗ này sâu lắm vào thế này thì
cured?
có phải phải khỏi thì phải cắt cái thi
I think it's very wide,
to đùi này vá lên Tôi nghĩ nó rộng lắm
four fingers wide, isn't it? It's not like
bốn đồng ngón tay cơ mà chứ có phải
in the summer, the burning season, these fingers are so big.
trong mùa hạ mùa đốt là ngón tay này to
Then I'm afraid of the rain. When I
lắm Thế lại sợ mưa đến lúc bắt đầu tu
start practicing, the disease still
tập thì bắt đầu tu tập thì bệnh nó vẫn
rots, the four places of the heart still rot, the flesh
cứ là thối bốn cái chỗ tâm vẫn thối thịt
rots, but the buttocks are on the feet, right? Yes,
thối nhưng Mông ở chân chứ gì Vâng đến
when I start practicing, it's still the same. The
lúc tu tập bắt đầu tu tập nó vẫn thế gì
formula was rotten from before, then I
công thức nó thối từ trước rồi xong mới
collected and practiced, and then it
sưu tập tu tập tu tập thì nó lại cứ thu
gradually shrank, it convulsed, it convulsed, it gradually shrank,
dần vào nó co giật vào nó nó co giật nó
it gradually healed, until it was
thu dần nó bồi Dần vào thế đến lúc vừa
cured, and then I could walk again. My dear fellow practitioners, do you
khỏi thế là cũng lại đi được các quý đạo
see how wonderful the Buddha's medicine is? The
hữu thấy thuốc của phật vi Diệu chưa
Buddha's teachings are profound and miraculous, are
pháp phật cao sâu rất nhiệm mầu đấy có
n't they?
phải không
I go to the market for the fellow practitioners, but they
em đi chợ duyên cho các đạo hữu thì còn
lock the door and won't let me in. That's because my
khóa cửa rồi không cho vào đấy là đấy là
husband
chồng
still doesn't trust me. I
vẫn không tin tưởng mà vẫn không tin
go to practice, I go to the market for the fellow practitioners,
em đi tu tập cho đi chợ duyên cho các
and they go to my private place. Is
bạn cũng như là các bạn đến chỗ riêng
it because I go to a spirit medium, I go singing, I
cho mình có phải là em đi đồng bóng em
go dancing, that they won't let me go? Is it because they won't
đi hát đi Múa gì đâu mà sao lại không
let me go?  I'm not going to the wrong path. No, that's
cho em đi có phải là em đi Tà kiến đâu
not it. This is going to the market for love,
Không phải đâu Đây là đi chợ duyên đấy
Phuoc Anh. So later, when he heard it,
Phước anh ạ thế là về sau Ông cũng nghe
he ate his meal and asked his grandson if he had served rice for
ra thì lại ăn cơm lại bảo thằng cháu nội
his grandmother yet, not if he had served
xới cơm cho bà chưa chứ không phải xới
rice for her to eat. That means we
cơm cho bà ăn đâu ạ Tức là chúng ta
[music]
[âm nhạc]
[laughter] [laughter]
[Tiếng cười]
Mother is practicing in front of the altar like this, and the child
mẹ tu ở trước mà bàn thờ thế này thì con
goes back and forth twice and doesn't see anything, doesn't
nó đi lại hai lần không thấy gì không
hear anything. Oh, so happy! Then, oh, the
thấy nó nói gì cả Ôi sướng quá rồi xong
child is praying to Buddha. I don't know if this place is the right place. I'm so
ô con bạch phật không biết là cái chỗ
happy, I don't know how far I've progressed in my
tức là mừng quá rồi không biết tu đến
practice, I don't know how far I've progressed, I don't know if I've progressed or not. So, I'm still at the place where I'm praying to Buddha. I'm praying again from the beginning. While chanting scriptures and practicing, I
thế là đang tụng kinh đang tu tập thì
see my child coming back, I'm so scared, so
thấy con nó đi lại thì sợ quá
happy, so happy, he doesn't object, so
sướng sướng quá vậy nó không phản đối
happy, I don't know how far I've progressed in my practice,
rồi mừng quá lên không biết là tu đến
so I'm
đâu rồi thế là thôi con bạch Phật con
praying to Buddha again from the beginning. Is
lại tu lại từ đầu
n't that a funny story?
đấy câu chuyện vui không
Now, my husband is going. Call him back
Bây giờ là chồng con đi Gọi lại bình
normally, no, no, he can cook, he can eat, he can
thường không không lại nấu được ăn lại
decide. He's cleaned up, he doesn't need a cane anymore, and
quyết được Dọn rồi không phải chống gậy
now every day is a
đâu mà bây giờ mỗi một ngày là trận đi
workout session.  It's almost two kilometers away, dear fellow
tập thể dục gần hai cây số đây các quý
practitioners. I spent four months practicing diligently,
đạo hữu không Công phu có bốn tháng trời
teaching from 4 AM each month, and yet I managed to eliminate
mỗi tháng dạy từ 4 giờ sáng mà tiêu được
the karma of cleaning up my husband's feces. He suffered so
cái nghiệp dọn cứt cho Chồng đã khổ rồi
much, and with all the medicine, he couldn't walk
bao nhiêu thuốc nữa chồng không đi được
anymore. It stinks, isn't that
nữa Thối thối thì ta có phải là đấy là
my karma?
nghiệp của mình nhé
Oh well, it smells bad. Let me
Thôi mà nó hôi đấy thế Ở đây tâm chưa
explain to you, dear fellow practitioners, this:
nhé giải thích cho các quý Đạo Hữu này
Your karma is having to care for a
nghiệp của đạo hữu là nghiệp phải chăm
sick person, enduring so much suffering,
người ốm như vậy phải chịu bao nhiêu cái
sleepless nights, the stench of
khổ như vậy đêm không ngủ được hôi thối
cleaning up feces. Isn't that right, dear fellow
dọn phân dọn cứt có đúng không các quý
practitioners? If you think it's right, this is your karma. If
đạo hữu thấy đúng đây là nghiệp của của
not, then if
đạo hữu không thì nghiệp như thế thì
you practice, you should transform that karma and
mình tu thì mình chuyển cái nghiệp ấy đi
dedicate it to your husband as
mình hồi hướng cho chồng là cộng nghiệp
your shared karma. So, if your karma is transformed, your
của mình Thế là nghiệp của mình chuyển
husband's karma will also be transformed. Now, I
thì chồng phải chuyển thôi Bây giờ tôi
practice. I have the karma of caring for my paralyzed husband.
tu Tôi có cái nghiệp là hầu chồng bị làm
I have the karma of having to spend money to
liệt Tôi có cái nghiệp nào phải mất tiền
buy medicine for my husband. I
để mà mua thuốc chữa bệnh cho chồng tôi
have the karma of suffering because my husband might die.
có cái nghiệp là phải đau khổ vì chồng
Now, if I cultivate and eliminate
chết mất Thế giờ tôi tu hết cái nghiệp
my karma, my husband will recover on his own. Is
với của tôi đi thì chồng tôi tự khỏi
n't that our shared karma? That's what we're doing.  We are cultivating our own karma, not our
khỏi không Đấy là chúng ta đang tu
husband's karma, but we are
của chồng nhưng mà chúng ta đang tu
cultivating our own karma. Isn't that how cultivation
nghiệp cho chúng ta đấy thì có phải tu
transforms things? Do you fellow practitioners agree?
nó chuyển hóa không các quý đạo hữu thấy
So, cultivation
đúng không nào đó cho nên có Tu là có
transforms karma. The karma that our children
chuyển
hindered us from practicing is transformed.
cái nghiệp bị con cấm cản tu tập đấy
We cultivate, and now we
mình tu rồi nó cũng chuyển bây giờ là
can practice freely and comfortably. Isn't it true that
được thênh thang thoải mái tu Thế có
within a family,
phải là trong gia đình là cộng nghiệp
we share karma? If we continue to cultivate, everyone's
với nhau mình mà cứ tu thì mọi người
situation will change. Our minds will focus on one thing.
việc nó sẽ chuyển đi tâm chiếu một quán
For example, if we have karma in
nói này Ví dụ mình có cái nghiệp là cuộc
our lives where our children mistreat us, are
đời mình mình bị con mình bị nó bạc đãi
unfilial, then of
mình nó bất hiếu mình phải không thì tất
course they will be even more unfilial. If they are unfilial, and we suffer the karma
nhiên là nó sẽ bạc đại Nó bất hiếu với
of being old and our children not
mình mình bị nghiệp là già rồi con không
having money to care for us, if
có tiền mà cho mình chăm bệnh nếu nghiệp
our karma becomes that our children don't have money to give
của mình thành các con nó không có tiền
us, then if we continue to cultivate our own karma, then our children will be free from the
cho mình thế giờ mình cứ Tu nghiệp của
mistreatment, and they will be
mình đi thì con hết cái nghiệp bị con
filial. Isn't that
bạc đại thì con có hiếu thấy có phải là
beneficial for both of us? We also receive the blessing of being cared for in our
lợi ích cả cho con không mình lại được
old age, with
cái Phước là già rồi Con được chăm có
money to care for us. Isn't that what helps our children succeed in their
tiền của Chăm mình thế có phải là khiến
work? Isn't that so?
cho con làm ăn được không có phải không
So, our cultivation is for the
Thế là mình tu có phải là cả để cả cho
benefit of our children as well.  No,
con mình được hưởng không phải không các
dear fellow practitioners, our family benefits, you know.
quý đạo hữu cái nhà mình được hưởng chứ
That's what you said, fellow practitioner.
nhé Đấy cái việc của Đạo Hữu nói lên cái
We see that the Buddha Dharma
sự việc này chúng ta thấy rằng Phật Pháp
saves us all from suffering; it's just a matter of whether
là cứu khổ hết tất cả ta chỉ có cái
we persevere in practicing or not. You just left, fellow practitioner, and then your nephew came down. He
chúng ta có kiên trì tu hay không thôi
ran down and told me to
thằng cháu xuống con ton chạy xuống là
tell my son to call home and
nói cho thằng con nó gọi điện về nó
not let me practice. But I'm still determined to practice because I'm
không cho tu vẫn kiên quyết tu vì mình
suffering so much. I've been everywhere, to
khổ quá rồi đi khắp các nơi rồi bệnh
hospitals, to make offerings everywhere, and I
viện đủ rồi cúng khai khắp nơi rồi cũng
've done so much, it's very expensive, but nothing has worked. So
có làm cái gì có tốn kém lắm mà không
now, I have to rely on the Buddha Dharma. In
Thế bây giờ thì phải Nương vào Phật pháp
the end, I have to rely on it,
cuối cùng thôi thì phải Nương vào thôi
right, dear fellow practitioners?
đúng không các quý đạo hữu đấy lợi ích
That's the benefit, dear fellow practitioners. On
như vậy đấy các quý đạo cái hôm hôm mùng
December 8th, 2020,
8 tháng 12 năm 20
Quân from Lãng down there, his daughter-in-law called home, "
thằng Quân của ở cái Lãng dưới đấy con
Mom, Mom, light incense for me." He's
dâu điện về Mẹ ơi mẹ thắp hương đi cho
looking for someone, but
con nhà con nó lại làm gì tìm hết người
nobody knows anything, and then they say, "What's the point of him dying like that?"
không biết gì rồi bảo chết thế làm gì
So I went to light incense and make offerings to Phú's hair.
rồi Thế là lên thắp hương tóc Phú cúng
Oh, I don't know what to say. I don't know, I just kept
dường rồi Ôi con không biết con bạch thế
crying and calling
lại khóc
Auntie Gạo, but she didn't come out. I called
điện cho cô gạo gạo chẳng trưởng không
again, and still nothing.  I don't
thấy ra điện tiếp tục điện nữa vẫn không
know, she was cursing at someone and trembling all over,
biết bà chửi người thì run hết lên rồi
and then the child was down there crying and saying she did
mà lại con thì ở dưới kia khóc rồi bảo
n't know anything, her face was all purple, and she didn't
là không biết gì tím hết người mà không
call or answer. So I called the
gọi không nghe rồi Thế lại tiếp tục gọi
rice lady again, and she said, "Have you
cho cô gạo lần nữa cô gạo bảo thế chị
entered yet?" "I don't know
vạch Vào chưa Vào Chị không biết bạch
how to enter, I'll ask you, I'll make you enter."
thế nào để hỏi em để em em bắt chị vạch
So she guided me, and inside
Thế là cô ấy lại hướng dẫn bài và trong
she said, "Tell the children that there's
thì cô lại bảo chị bảo người ta các cháu
someone outside pressing the acupoint on
nó có đứa nào ở ngoài nó bấm cái huyệt ở
this nose." So I called my
ở ở mũi này nhá Thế thế là cũng gọi cho
daughter-in-law, and at that time,
con dâu thế là con dâu lúc bây giờ là 10
around 10 o'clock, 11:30, the child woke up, the
giờ hơn 10 giờ 11:30 thì cháu tỉnh chú
uncle woke up, but I still didn't believe her. My
cháu tỉnh thì em vẫn không tin nó đứa
eldest daughter-in-law came down from Tan Hoa,
con dâu cả ở trên Tân Hoa đi xuống cách
10 kilometers away. The two of them came
đấy 10 cây số xuống đấy hai nghe hai vợ
down and said, "Mom, go back to sleep,
chồng nó xuống và mẹ ơi mẹ ngủ đi nhá
Uncle is awake." "Mom, I don't believe you,
chú tỉnh rồi còn không Mẹ không tin mày
give the phone to him so I
đưa điện thoại đi cho cho nó để cho mẹ
can hear his voice, then I'll believe you, Mom. I'm
được nghe tiếng của nó thì mẹ mới tin mẹ
fine, I'm awake,
ơi con không làm sao đâu con tỉnh rồi
I can eat porridge now." "Oh, okay, okay, then I
con ăn được cháo rồi À ừ thế Ừ thế thì
'll believe you." "Did you guys get the color wrong?" It was in
mẹ mới tin đấy các cậu có nhầm màu chưa
the middle of the night.  Then, when the body turns purple, the woman
thôi Nó Nửa đêm rồi mà tím hết người cô
says it's soft and unresponsive, and the person doesn't know anything,
bảo mềm đi rồi mà không biết gì gọi
doesn't know anything at all, that's
không biết gì hết thì cái lúc đấy là cái
when we're affected by karma, maybe
lúc chúng ta bị cái nghiệp có thể là cái
our karma is coming. But if
nghiệp của chúng ta nó đến nhưng chúng
we repent in time, and accumulate merit,
ta kịp thời sám hối kịp thời tác Phước
our merit will increase, and
Cái Phước của chúng ta nó tăng thì chúng
we can influence
ta có thể là tác động trên trên trên
our bodies or use
trên thân thể của chúng ta hoặc có thuốc
medicine to transform it. Because life
men gì thì nó sẽ chuyển hóa vì là sống
or death depends on our merit, so when something happens, the
hay chết là do cái Phước báo cho nên khi
first thing
chúng ta cứ có cái việc gì đầu tiên
we do is repent. We must know that
chúng ta sám hối đã chúng ta phải biết
karma is due to our past sins. The
nghiệp là do tội ác của chúng ta quá khứ
first thing we react to is repentance. After that,
đầu tiên chúng ta phản ứng ngay là sám
we begin to offer prayers and dedicate the merit. If we do
hối đã xong rồi chúng ta bắt đầu bạch ở
n't know how to dedicate it to the Buddha, we
hồi hướng đấy không biết bạch Phật là
tremble, dear fellow practitioners.
lúc đấy nó run các quý đạo hữu ạ Thế
However, every day we must practice to get
nhưng mà hàng ngày chúng ta phải Huân
used to it. We sincerely repent, for
tập cho nó quen đi chúng con Thành Tâm
everything that happens to us
Sám Hối tất cả cái gì đến với chúng con
is due to karmic retribution. We repent to our enemies and those who
là do nghiệp báo chúng con sám hối với
are seeking revenge.
các Oan Gia Trái Chủ đang thì báo oán
We repent so that
như thế này chúng con sám hối để cho
we may find a doctor and medicine to cure our illness. Then
chúng con gặp thầy gặp thuốc chữa bệnh
we ask for merit, make offerings, and
rồi chúng con xin tác Phước cúng dường
practice afterwards.  This story is
rồi tu tập sau này con chuyện nó qua đi
a bit over, and I'm practicing
một tí là con tu tập là con xin tu tập
repentance and dedicating the merits to it.
Sám Hối hồi hướng công đức đấy nôm Na
That's all, dear fellow practitioners. Just be
thế thôi các quý đạo hữu ạ nôm Na thôi
sincere. And then you talk about transformation.
thành tâm thôi đã thế mà nói chuyển hóa
That's like the story of a fellow
Đấy tức là giống như cái câu chuyện mà
practitioner whose autistic grandchild transformed. I told my
nhà đạo hữu mà có cháu tự kỷ mà chuyển
enemies, "Just go to the temple first. I'll offer
oan gia cứ về chùa trước đi Tôi là cúng
money, but I'll leave it here. I'll
tiền lên nhưng tiền tôi cứ để đây rồi
bring it back when I go home." It's that simple.
Hôm nào về tôi mang về mộc mạc thế thôi
Thanks to your remedy, my husband and son
nhờ cái bài thuốc của cô mà chồng con
are cured. He said, "My wife, I don't know
lại khỏi anh ấy bảo em vợ không biết anh
what you did, but you're all itchy and covered in rashes." Then
làm gì mà ngứa mẩn hết người đến rồi
I thought, "Ah,
xong rồi Thế em với lại nghĩ sao mà À
your remedy... I saw it on my phone."
bài thuốc của cô cô ở trên điện thoại
So I wrote it down in this notebook to pray to
thế là em ghi ra quyển sổ này để em Bạch
Buddha, and then I'll treat him with your remedy. The rashes came on, one by one, and
Phật xong em chữa bài thuốc của cô cho
then his whole body, his whole hands, and everything. Then I
mảng từng mảng một xong cũng hoàn cả
took some
người cả thân cả tay thế là mới lấy lá
guava leaves, the hairy guava leaves you gave me, and crushed them for him to
mơ có lấy lá mơ lông của cô đấy chứ vò
drink. Yesterday was the third day. So
cho uống hôm qua hôm qua là ngày thứ ba
today I went to the temple to
của Thế hôm nay em đi về chùa thì em đi
get the leaves, and he boiled them himself.  The
lấy lá về thì anh tự đun xong mình thống
best thing to do is take a bath with the leaves. No, he's cured.
nhất vò tắm nhé Không anh khỏi rồi cái
This is truly a dream, dear fellow practitioners.
này thực là mơ đấy các quý Đạo Hữu
Dear fellow practitioners, the mind-viewing and complete contemplation are
Kính thưa các quý đạo hữu thì tâm chiếu
very auspicious. Whenever you
Hoàn quán rất là có duyên cứ khi mà các
have any illness, you ask the Buddha to
đạo hữu có bệnh gì thì cũng bạch Phật để
see what cures it. For example, if
xem xem là cái bệnh này chữa được bằng
someone has an
cái gì thì có cái bệnh tức là người mà
itchy rash and keeps getting pimples that won't go away,
mẩn ngứa xong cứ nổi mụn lên đấy không
just crush the leaves of the plum tree,
khỏi đấy thì chỉ cần là vò cái lá mơ dã
drink the juice, and bathe with the plum tree leaves, and
lá mơ uống lấy nước và lấy lá mơ tắm thì
it will be cured. You'll be cured in
nó khỏi đấy Các mẹ Hữu
three days. So we have a great karmic
ba ngày khỏi đấy cho nên chúng ta rất có
connection, don't we, dear fellow practitioners?
duyên với nhau phải không quý đạo hữu sẽ
To be clear, dear fellow
có duyên với nhau ạ Để Kính thưa quý đạo
practitioners, through this story, we
hữu qua cái câu chuyện này thì chúng ta
see that you are very struggling. Your
thấy rằng đạo hữu lở rất là vất vả Vừa
husband is sick, you are practicing Buddhism, and your child is
chồng ốm và tu tập Phật Pháp lại còn con
hindering you. Now you are
cản trở chồng cản trở thế Bây giờ chúng
suffering so much, you have nothing left but the
ta khổ quá rồi không còn cái gì ngoài
lifeline of Buddhism. So you
tấm phao Phật pháp cả cho nên là kiên
persevered to the end, and now you have achieved
trì đến cuối cùng bây giờ là thành công
brilliant success. Your husband's illness is cured, your
rực rỡ bệnh của chồng việc thì khỏi cứu
child's life is saved, and now you can
được mạng của con rồi bây giờ lại được
practice. The whole family supports you. Therefore, nothing is
tu tập Cả nhà ủng hộ Thế cho nên không
without effort.
Cái gì là là không phải bỏ công sức ra
With faith and heavy karma, you must
đâu có lòng tin nghiệp nặng thì phải
persevere for a long time.  That's right, the mind must be
kiên trì lâu đấy mà cái tâm nó phải
focused, my fellow practitioners. No matter what,
chuyên nhất đấy đạo hữu Dù gì đi chăng
persevere to the end, but
nữa vẫn kiên tâm đến cùng nhưng mà cũng
some new practitioners may encounter obstacles and fear.
có một số đạo hữu mới có cản trở sợ hãi
Well, I'll ask my family for permission. I'll take a
Thôi tôi xin gia đình tôi như thế Tôi
temporary break. A
xin nghỉ tạm thời gian nghỉ nó có hết
break won't erase all karma, will it? That's how you cultivate to achieve
nghiệp đâu phải không Đấy tu như này mới
transformation. So, I'm also encouraging all you esteemed
chuyển hóa Thế qua đây cũng sách tấn các
practitioners to be diligent. This is a
quý đạo hữu được tinh tấn Đây là một
message from the Buddha's teachings to
thông điệp của phật pháp gửi đến cho
us: all our evil karma,
chúng ta tất cả các ác nghiệp của chúng
born from beginningless time until now, is now coming
ta đã sinh ra từ vô thủy kiếp đến nay
to an end. Only the
rồi bây giờ đến thời trả quả chỉ có Phật
Buddha's teachings can help us transform it,
Pháp mới giúp chúng ta chuyển hóa được
and the Buddha's teachings are a solid foundation
thôi và Phật Pháp là nơi tựa vững chắc
for us in this life and many
cho chúng ta kiếp này cho tới nhiều kiếp
future lives. If we have wisdom,
vị lai sau chúng ta có trí giác thì
we will be happy.
chúng ta sẽ được hạnh phúc không nên bản
We should know that we ourselves create
thân chúng ta biết tự chúng ta tạo
karma, so we must cultivate ourselves to
nghiệp thì tự chúng ta phải tu hành nó
transform it.
mới có thể chuyển hóa được nghiệp nhé
I wish you all diligent practice.
chúc các quý đạo hữu tinh tấn
Respectfully, my esteemed practitioners, today we
kính thưa quý đạo hữu hôm nay chúng ta
had a very beneficial session, didn't we?
có một buổi rất là bổ ích phải không Cái
Everything...  We must experience and know the truth
gì thì cũng phải trải nghiệm và sự thật
before we can believe. Without
thì chúng ta mới tin được không có sự
truth, we cannot believe. Buddhism
thật thì không thể tin được mà đạo Phật
is the true path, isn't it?
là đạo chân thật mà phải không đạo Phật
Buddhism is the path of doing, not of
là thật đạo Phật là đạo làm không phải
talking. If we come to
đạo nói các đạo hữu Nếu chúng ta đến
Buddhism just to listen and enjoy it, then we
phật pháp chúng ta chỉ nghe nói cho nó
are not truly
hay thì Quả thật không phải là người tu
Buddhist practitioners. To truly practice Buddhism, we must practice
phật mà tu Phật phải tự mình thực hành
and experience the
và tự mình trải nghiệm được những cái
happiness that comes from the Dharma ourselves. Only then can we be truly
điều hạnh phúc từ Phật Pháp mới thật sự
Buddhist practitioners. We should be proud to
là người tu Phật chúng ta hãnh diện
be practitioners of Buddhism,
chúng ta là người tu tập Phật pháp chứ
not just people who come to
không phải chỉ là người đến với Phật
Buddhism to listen for fun. May
pháp để nghe cho nó vui nhé
everyone in our club
Chúc câu lạc bộ của chúng ta ai ai cũng
be happy.
được hạnh phúc
[Music]
[âm nhạc]